this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
or / software and welcome to software
engineering radio hello could you start
us off with some brief history of go
sure
well for those of you that don't know my
name is Andrew and I work on the core
programming language and have done for
the last four years go was actually
started at Google I guess
nearly six years ago maybe even a little
earlier as a sort of side project by Rob
Pike Robert Griezmann and Kenton
Thompson and they kind of packed on it
sort of on the side for a while and then
it gradually became their full-time
thing and then we added a few more
people to the team at the next couple of
years and released it as an open source
project in November 2009 and we actually
just celebrated our fourth anniversary
of that release on Sunday so it's now
been an open source project for the last
four years about two years after the
release we released go 1.0 that was
actually last year in 2012 in march and
that was our sort of big stable release
and since then we've done a couple of
major releases were actually heading
towards the second major release 1.2 a
couple of weeks time but yeah we've seen
a lot of growth a huge amount of
engagement from the open source
community
we actually have nearly 400 contributors
to the project the open source project
and we have a very active sort of
non-google development team as well so
there's a bunch of people what's still
working in full time on go at Google and
also a lot of people outside
contributing to the project - and what
were some of the objectives of the
language's founders when the project
initially got started well I mean it was
there's a joke that go was conceived
while waiting for a C++ program to
compile which is kind of half true but
basically go grew from a dissatisfaction
with the development environments
languages that we were using at Google
none of them and really been designed
well for one recently I mean C++ and
Java is there for more than a decade old
whether at stage two in ghostbusters
case but none of these environments that
we had were really designed to work at
the scale at which we're working at
Google and you know everyone knows and
thinks about Google in terms of scale of
users and scale of servers but one thing
that's not talked about as often is the
scale of engineering effort so we have
you know many many thousands of
programmers working on huge huge code
bases and they're largely just one big
shared code base and that we all sort of
work on and so know no language was
designed to worry this kind of scale and
so there are a lot of issues and a lot
of kind of awful workarounds we've had
to employ to simply function at this
kind of organizational scale and so go
was really an opportunity to think about
a lot of the problems that we've
encountered working at this scale and
design a language and also design an
environment that really works and so one
really good example of this is go font
so go from stands to go format and it's
a tool that just takes any go source
file and freely prints it in the
canonical or formatting style so it
means that your go code looks the same
as anybody else's go code you can easily
read other people's code bases you don't
have to talk about brace placement or
indentation or any of those kind of
nitpicky things in code reviews it's all
just kind of taken care of for you and
so that that was one of the things that
was designed into language from start
and there are many other such examples
in goes design that really make it
easier to collaborate and to sort of
write code bases of massive scale I
imagine these things help when starting
to build editors and maybe debugging
tools for working with go so the
language is designed to be easy to pause
and by extension azb just sort of
mechanical any manipulate source code so
we have a growing suite of tools for
actually positing and processing and
computing on on go source code and so
that's
definitely one of the design goals and
languages to make tooling really easy
yeah we've seen a lot of really nice
tools for instance a recent tool that
was just released by a couple of the go
team members is called go imports and
you can just feed a go program through
it and it automatically updates the
package import statements in the file to
add or remove the relevant imports
depending on what other packages you're
using in the code and so it uses a bunch
of heuristics to figure out like which
other libraries you wanted to be using
and then adds those import statements to
the file and so it really takes a lot of
the friction out of working with you
know other people's code and just coding
in general and especially dealing with
large dependency libraries and waiting
for the build times of enormous C++
projects was one of the motivations for
creating the language in the first place
you know that seems especially yeah yeah
also so well that particular problem for
the people that don't know is that to
compile a C or a C++ program any file
that includes a header file it needs to
effectively repass that header file
while parsing the file that includes it
and so this kind of grows quadratically
with your code base and so it gets to
the point where your repassing thousands
and thousands of lines of header files
just to include dependencies that you've
already looked at in the compilation
stages and so go as designed so that
each package objects each actual
compiled object emitted by the compiler
contains all the information required to
describe the transitive closure of its
dependencies so if you have a dependency
tree that's like a imports B which
imports C you can make changes to be a
recompile a it will recompile B but it
doesn't even need to look at C again and
so it kind of prunes that dependency
tree and sort of means that your build
system can more aggressively reuse all
the build artifacts and so that's
definitely like one of them the major
design goals of go is to not do more
work than is actually necessary and it's
kind of something that wasn't really
thought about Wednesday was designed in
the first place so we got to sort of fix
that issue and go can you describe how
interfaces work and go
yes so go has an interesting object
model so guys is certainly an object
oriented language but if you come from
say a Java or a C++ background you might
find the approach a little different
because for instance car doesn't have
classes it doesn't have a notion of
inheritance in the same way and so the
way you structure programs and go is
typically quite different to the way you
structure them in sort of the classical
object-oriented languages the linchpin
of goes object model is interfaces and
the way interfaces work and go is that
you specify an interface type which
contains some method specifications and
so a classic one is the i/o reader
interface from the standard library
which defines one method
it's a read method and anything which
kind of provides a stream of bytes will
typically implement this read method but
when they implement it they don't need
to specify that they implement it simply
the fact of implementing that method of
that specific specification means that
it implements the i/o reader so there's
no implements declaration and so this
has a really nice effect of decoupling
pieces of code you don't sort of have
this kind of rigid system of declaring
interface in one place and then wherever
you implement declaring it instead you
can be a bit more loose about it you can
declare interfaces in a sort of post hoc
fashion like when you discover that
there are similarities between certain
types and you want to use them in the
same way you can just declare an
interface there and then and then use
them as those interface types instead of
having to go back and add your
implements declarations back and so it's
kind of a difficult worldview to
assimilate just by thinking about it you
really intercept to get your hands dirty
and use it a bit but the end result of
it is the go objects tend to have fewer
responsibilities and tend to be a lot
small than objects in other languages
and we tend to build systems not by
building type hierarchies but instead by
building small pieces that satisfy small
interfaces and then composing them
together and I think this is a really
kind of subtle but
ultimately profound shift in focus to
the way a lot of people have been
writing software for a long time
for me personally it's been usually
beneficial I found that the code that I
ran in gogo is a lot simpler and a lot
more reliable than the current I was
writing before in other languages were
their initial frustrations when you were
trying to design your code around such a
different interface system well I mean
it certainly helps that I had you know
the design of the language the designers
of the language sitting next to me at
the time but really it by the time I'd
gotten to go I've kind of become a
little bit dissatisfied with the kind of
Hoops that a lot of these our
environments were making me jump through
and I was using Python and JavaScript
pretty heavily at the time so everything
that I was doing was fairly
unconventional I guess by that stage so
it wasn't it wasn't a stretch to kind of
move into into go and sort of adopt this
different approach the main thing that I
think people have trouble with coming
into go is just letting go of previous
kind of techniques that they had used to
structure things because there are a lot
of design patterns associated with
object-oriented programming and I think
in in go you're sort of left more to
just write the code that works that not
worry so much about the structure of it
at least initially and then what happens
typically when writing code code is the
structure kind of emerges over time and
you're able to sort of codify things a
bit more defined some interfaces kind of
becomes a more formal later on instead
of starting off with this kind of formal
design yeah it almost sounds like it's
readability oriented code rather than
concurrency oriented or object oriented
code certainly the language is like a
readability oriented language Vishal can
you tell me about the relationship
between arrays and slices why did you
settle on using them as a way to have
fixed and variable length arrays and how
does this relate to static typing yes
serger has arrays in slices and arrays
are kind of like Pascal arrays and that
they have the size of the array as part
of the type declaration so if you
declare a variable of type like five
intz then it's just an array of five
integers and
big groan it can't be shrunk and so
there are situations where that's useful
like if you wanted to declare a pixel of
RGB you might have an array of three
byte values and you're not going to need
more or less so that that makes sense
but in situations where you want to work
with arrays of varying lengths where
this mechanism called slices and a slice
is basically a view to own an array and
so if you allocate a slice it actually
allocates an array and then you get this
slice value to the points of the array
and the slice value includes the length
of the view to the array and so you can
be seeing you know elements 1 through 4
or or you can race lice to see fewer or
more of those elements and the backing
rain and to grow a slice you are they
ray slice the slice and to see more of
the backing array or if you're out of
space in the backing array you
reallocate and copy to a new backing
array and you get a slice value that
points to this new backing array and so
it's kind of a compromise between you
know the real felicity of programming
that you get from say pythons lists
which are a very simple programming
model some strange rough edges in places
but mostly you can just use them and I
really think about them very much but go
slices kind of make you think a bit more
about what the machines doing but what
you get in exchange is absolute control
over the allocation characteristics of
your program so you know whenever you
may be allocating more memory or copying
or not when working with slices they're
one of the few novel things and go as a
language and I think they they work
really well and how does go manage
concurrency well so concurrency is one
of the big features of go as a language
and it's concurrency model is based
around two fundamental elements one of
them is goroutines which are a
lightweight thread like a green thread
that managed by the go runtimes so
typically you'll have tens hundreds even
thousands of go routines multiplexed
across fewer operating system threads so
the idea is you would have pretty much
as many operating system threads as
there are CPUs in your machine and so
you know as threads are quite expensive
and so you
you want to only have as many as you
need for that parallelism but then the
dota code actually runs in these very
teens which they're quite small I mean
they start off around for a K so you can
generally create and destroy their
routines as often as you like without
really thinking about it what that lets
you do is write concurrent code in just
a top-down sort of straightforward style
but you get the behavior of like an
event-driven framework so your code can
block but the runtime just immediately
moves any blocking code away from being
executed and then execute some code that
can run and so you know you you get that
kind of really nice the high-performance
concurrency that you get from saying no
js' but you can run across multiple
threads and you can just write your code
in a normal top-down style you don't
need to get into call backs upon call
backs upon call backs and so it leads to
a really comprehensible programming
model but with efficient runtime
characteristics and so that's the go
routines part and then to communicate
between curry teams we have another
primitive called channels which are
basically just like a typed pipe where
you can send go values through and so if
one girl routine does a sender on a
channel another girl routine can do a
receive from that channel and in a
thread safe way they can pass data back
and forth and they can also be
synchronized because the send and
receive must happens simultaneously and
so channel is from it's arrived from
cause communicating sequential processes
which is a seminal paper and concurrent
programming from I guess the seventies
maybe if in the late sixties if you
haven't used them before it's kind of a
bit of a high opening experience thanks
to write concurrent code with channels
because it really lets you model
concurrent processes which is typically
you know real-world processes in a way
that is just very straightforward and
easy to understand are the analogous to
any features in other languages Erlang
has mailboxes which are kind of similar
you can communicate between processes in
Erlang in a similar kind of way although
their execution model is is quite
different there have been some previous
languages that provide these kind of
features that Rob Mike
one of them is LF and another is new
squeak there's libraries that provide
very similar kinds of concurrency
mechanisms in other environments like
their I think like a live event to see
might provide something similar but none
of them really work in precisely the
same way as go routines channels due to
the particular implementation in this
stage in Goa is quite unique I think you
touched on this a little bit earlier but
could you talk a little more about how
imports work and go yeah so basically
one of the goals of go as a tool chain
and as an environment is that you should
need to maintain like make files or
other kinds of metadata files to define
the way to build your programs and so
the go tool chain kind of uses a
convention of all of the files that
comprise they go package so a go package
is a unit of code code it contains types
and functions variables and constants
and so ago has adjacent package as an
HTTP package it has a string formatting
package all of these packages each live
in their own directory and the directory
is relative to some root over tree and
when you import that package you
actually imported by the path of that
directory relative to the root so all
the standard library packages have these
short import parts like the string
formatting package is just fmt the HTTP
package is net slash HTTP and when
you're writing your own packages you'll
typically put them inside what's called
a workspace in a directory that somehow
uniquely identify as your organization
so me personally for my own code I keep
things on github so my import parts
typically begin with github.com slash my
username slash whatever the repository
name is and so when I import my code I'm
actually importing it by its full like
universally unique path so the the first
major benefit of this is that from the
source code the tool it's called the go
tool which you can use to build and test
and so on the go tool can resolve all of
those dependencies just by looking at
the source code because the import paths
describe completely everything that's
needed to locate those packages and so
that means that you you don't
to maintain make files you don't need to
maintain any kind of build files the
code says everything it needs to about
that but one of the really nice benefits
of this is that you can use the go tool
to fetch remote code from their
repositories so you know if someone
imports one of my packages using the
github import path I can use the goat
once they go get this package and it
will resolve the URL at a URL from the
import path fetch that package from the
repository and then do the same thing
recursively and so resolve all of the
dependencies in that way and so we get
this kind of nice
decentralized mechanism for fetching
third-party code and you know it has its
limitations like it doesn't support any
kind of versioning and relies on people
keeping the you know the head revision
of their repository T in a useful stage
and in a consistent state so it's not
perfect and there are there are tools
for help managing versions after you
fetch the packages but as far as you
know identifying code and identifying
packages that I think it's a really nice
design and one that people tend to
really like once they've gotten used to
it it does actually force you to keep
your code in prescribed flows in your
file system and some people don't like
being told what their code in this
specific place they have their habits
and they want to keep things you know
where they used to keeping them but I
think once you kind of let go of that
and just adopt the same convention as
everyone else things become remarkably
straightforward and what about garbage
collection how does the garbage
collection system and go compare to that
of other languages also go is a garbage
collector language like a lot of the
scripting languages like Java and doors
garbage collector is pretty simple it
behaves pretty predictably it says stop
the world garbage collector so no using
hard runs while it's collecting garbage
but it's a very efficient stop - or
garbage collected and so it tends to
perform pretty well I mean it's it
hasn't seen all of the engineering
effort that's gone into say Java is jvn
garbage collector but one distinct
advantage that Gore has over a lot of
other garbage collector languages it is
something that I mentioned before which
is control over memory allocations as a
go program
it's very easy for you to see when
garbage is being created and the
language gives you the tools you need to
reuse memory where appropriate and to
avoid allocations and so even though
ghost garbage collector isn't you know
as advanced as that of some other
environments you also don't need to put
as much pressure on an in go you can
simply avoid creating a lot of the
garbage in the first place and we have
some really nice profiling tools for
profiling memory allocations and seeing
where the garbage is coming from and
once you know where it comes from the
language gives you the tools that you
need to reuse memory where you can and
you know avoid those allocations to
avoid putting the pressure on the GC so
you know it's it's a very different
model to say in Java where you have an
application and you really tune the JVM
SGC to get good performance it's kind of
harder in Java to tune the application
because there's a lot of allocations
that are just impossible to avoid I'm
they baked into some of Java's core IPS
is it on the roadmap at all to improve
the garbage collector is that sort of
more of like an ancillary concern and
you know it's absolutely on the agenda
to improve it and you know it has
improved from release to release we had
some dramatic speed ups in one point one
we should see some further precision
improvements in one point two as well as
some performance improvements but these
have all been incremental upon the
original design there are plans to you
know implement a new GC but I think that
will require some cooperation from the
compiler as well and I at the moment
we're really talking about improving the
compiler and you know porting the
compiler from C to go because it was
originally written in C it makes
bootstrapping a lot easier that way but
we think you know it's about time that
we did a go version of the compiler and
then you know once we have that at some
little maturity I think will be easier
to approach improving the GC because GC
implementations tend to be pretty
closely tied to the code generation
stage and so I think that's really the
first thing that needs to happen let's
discuss the compilation of of a go
program like I don't know how to
approach the discussion without going
too deep into the weeds but maybe you
can provide some overview also right now
the design is the
there's the compile of a stage which
takes in ghost source files and produces
a package object file and a package
object file is not machine code this is
the state right now it's not machine
code it's actually a kind of
intermediate assembly language so it's
all similar at all the Java bytecode
yeah except it's it's not by a code for
a virtual machine it's like assembly
instructions for a real machine but
they're not exactly the same as the
instructions that get emitted this sort
of halfway there you know so it's like
the compiler almost does some assembly
in the compiling compilation stage but
then it leaves the rest for the linkers
so the linker takes these object files
in discards any unused code from the
from the packages and then actually
translates that intermediate assembly
into machine code and the translation
itself is not tremendously different
from what comes in but it is different
and so this is a kind of unusual design
which we inherited from the plan nine
city compiler which is what the compiler
toolchain is currently written in now
and this was a design that Ken Thompson
built I guess in the in the late 90s or
early 2000s I probably only in the 90s
yeah
and yes we do more work on the compiler
we'll probably move to it a different
approach maybe a more traditional
approach of actually having the compiler
emit machine code rather than this kind
of intimate reformat you know it's not
my area of expertise and so I'm not sure
like which direction we will go to there
but it certainly is unusual I'm the way
it works now it's a very unconventional
compiler design that's for sure I have
some specific questions about the
operators of the language and I know
these are all in the documentation but
probably worth discussing some quick
ones that are they stick out as soon as
you kind of start messing around with
the language so there's the equals
operator which is just the assignment
operator but there's also a colon equals
which is the short variable declaration
how do these two differ well in colon
equals is used to declare variables and
you're declaring them with some initial
value so you know the call
is kind of important because it shows
that you're creating a new name in that
scope but equals is purely for
assignment so you have some name on the
left-hand side and then some value on
the right-hand side um and so you know
they're similar in function except the
colon equals also declares the name so
it's hard to do it just by talking but
like colon equals is actually a
shorthand for the variable declaration
statement which begins with the VAR
keyword so you know you could have var X
int to declare an X variable that's an
integer if you want to give it some
initial value you could say vy x int
equals 1 so you give it the initial
value of 1
but then the shorthand for that
statement is just x colon equals 1 and
so the you can drop the VAR keyword you
just have the name the colon equals and
the initial value and then the type of
that variable is inferred from the value
that you give it so because I'm giving
anyone it in first that this is an
integer variable and so most variable
declarations in go are done with the
colon equals operator but it's really
just like a shorthand for the more
explicit variable declarations in text
that we have and another question why is
there no ternary operator basically for
readability you know using the question
mark : the ternary form that you see in
C or JavaScript or something
it lets you write these really he sort
of terse turst lines that can do quite a
lot I mean you can put function calls in
there and they get short-circuited based
on you know the the conditions so as a
result you know you can kind of pack a
lot of functionality into a very small
piece of space and that's especially so
when you are using multiple ternary
operators in the one big expression and
you know you see people doing that and
frankly I think it's pretty awful I mean
I've always sort of felt that can be
kind of taken to a unnatural extreme and
go as a language generally tries to
discourage those kind of awfulness is
simply by making them impossible to do I
mean it's still possible to write really
ugly go code that's for sure but
generally when there have been features
like this that are very minor language
features just syntactical features we
tend to leave them out because it just
makes a language more complex it means
there's yet another thing you need to
know
another thing you need to think about
when reading the code and so you know
the the alternative is just to use an if
statement and if statements are very
easy to read very easy to understand and
you know it's a lot easier to see at a
glance what's happening in an if
statement where it is you know with the
question mark : you can bury a lot
inside that small space and this is the
same motivation for not having the
prefix operator I assume you know having
plus plus I yeah so we don't have like a
pre increment we just have an increment
so you can say I plus plus but not plus
plus I write and work well yeah yeah but
the main the main reason we don't have
that is actually because I plus plus and
go is not an expression so you can't
actually take the value of that
statement it's just a statement that you
must have on a line or in a for loop or
something but it's not a value it
doesn't doesn't evaluate to anything and
so the notion of the pre increment or
post increment is irrelevant because if
you can't take its value it doesn't
matter whether you're pre-incrementing
or post incrementing you're just
incrementing and so that's that decision
not to make the increment and expression
is actually very much in the name of
readability if you want to increment
something and then get the value of it
you need to do exactly that you need to
increment it and then take the value of
the variable when you don't have to
think about oh did I pre increment or
post increment or what yeah that's
that's another little syntactic thing
that we did in the name of free today
and it makes card a little bit more for
boats but it also makes it a little bit
more explicit to tell me about the
languages development process on a day
to day basis the development of the
language itself has slowed considerably
because after we did go 1.0 we've made a
compatibility promise that we won't
break any code so if your code the
compiles go 1.0 it should compile with
go one point x period you know we
anticipated that the go one point x line
will continue many years and we don't
you know we know that like go version
two is probably on the horizon somewhere
and it's you know we mark certain issues
on the issue trackers being go-to issues
simply by being backward incompatible or
set it outside of the scope of one
but it means that you know there's not a
lot of really sort of major work we can
do another language without adding a lot
of things a major point of goes
development is that had tried to only
include things that were really
necessary
in the design manner was designed by
consensus the consensus of the original
core team and then later as more members
were added to the team you know if
anybody has any major reservations if
anybody doesn't buy into the feature
suggestions and we just don't do it that
meant that a lot of features took a
really long time to design I mentioned
how long it took to design slices but at
the end of the day it means that we have
a language that is really small you can
learn it really easily and you know it's
it's easier to define and it easy to
implement yeah so as far as the
development of language is not really
like a huge amount happening day-to-day
we we have made a couple of language
changes in this coming release and in
the previous release but you know
they're really just tightening up what's
already there or you know maybe we
finally figured out how to do a certain
thing that we've been thinking about for
some time but you know most of the
action is really happening on the
compilers on the runtime and on the
libraries and tools and in particular on
the tools and so you know on the project
each contributor has the kind of area of
expertise you know some contributors
just hack on you know like fixing bugs
as they come in you know just kind of
doing small sort of cleanup sort of
stuff other contributors have you know
sort of broad areas of responsibility
where they're working on improvements to
the runtime or building new tools or
building new libraries and so there's a
lot of work going on in this stuff that
makes the language fun to work with
it's the tools that didn't make it
possible for you to really have a good
time programming in code and that's kind
of where our focus is on a day to day
basis right now what are some of those
tools like are you talking about like an
IDE or a debugger or well so a range of
different things I mean this there's
some people who are working on static
analysis tools so you know looking at
some ghost source code you can ask
questions like what is the type of this
variable you know where is it used look
at a function you know where is this
called does it satisfy name the faces
that those kinds of things and that will
feed into support for editor
and support for other development
environments we're not working on an IDE
per se but we're working on a lot of the
support stuff that should make that
possible other areas so in go 1.2 which
is coming out soon we include a new form
of profiling so we already had CPU
profile and memory profiling and block
profiling so being able to see where a
program is blocking and we have you know
a nice tool for visualizing those
profiling those profiles of that data so
you can see a nice sort of tree of where
allocations are or where the CPU time
has gone the new sort of hardness in 1.2
is test coverage profiling so you can
generate a profile of which code paths
your tests are exercising and you know
we have a tool that lets you view that
stuff you know where browser so you can
look at a kind of colorized version of
your source code to see you know which
paths are not being exercised by the
test you can see you know how heavily
they're being exercised as well and so
that's a really nice step towards
improving code quality just giving
people the tools to see whether they're
actually testing what they think they
are so that's an exciting addition that
will see this round I also mentioned
they've got imports tool for
automatically adding or removing imports
that saves a lot of fussing around just
when hacking on code because you're
typically you know add and remove
imports all the time and you know the
program won't compile unless you have
the correct imports stated at the top of
the file and so not having to think
about that it's a huge benefit how fully
featured is the standard library it's
pretty great a lot of people say that
the standard library is probably going
to best feature it has most stuff in it
that I need for a lot of the things that
I do and I write web apps I write my own
tools you know if you want to write say
like an OpenGL application obviously we
don't provide OpenGL in the standard
library but we do provide you know
everything you need to write a good
Network server basically translated
networking HTTP stuff encoding and
decoding of things like XML and JSON you
know that's a there's a quite a long
list of useful stuff in there that's
really just worth checking out rather
than me trying to rattle off a list of
names
yeah we kind of have what we think is a
pretty nice to handle library now it's
kind of well-rounded but now we're sort
of focusing development of new packages
on external auditor ease because we sort
of have this nice mechanism for
importing external libraries and
fetching them so you know there's very
little friction between using the
standard library or using any other
library are there some projects that
company like actual companies are using
go for in production like big companies
of course Google but I guess other
companies sure I mean I just published a
blog post a few days ago where I named a
few one of the really nice examples is
CloudFlare who were a content
distribution network essentially so you
know you hire them to basically serve
your website and they will use their
global caching system to deliver your
content really really fast where the
users are but then it all sort of goes
back to your servers eventually and you
sort of see some fraction of the overall
load and they've built structure in go
and you know recently published a blog
post talking about how they've enjoyed
using that other companies that use go
include like SoundCloud they're a big go
user written about it a lot a bunch of
startups have started using go so who
couple of recent examples were popped
hip and slice if you search for like
going go users or something like that
you should find there's a wiki page
which lists a huge number of these
people and some other people include
like Mozilla are using go canonical the
people that make Ubuntu have written a
lot of stuff and go as well BBC
Worldwide you know there's there's a
sort of growing list of people who are
adopted go for serious production work
and that's possibly the most satisfying
thing about it having worked on this
project is seeing all this all these
people picking up and really enjoying
using go do you think they pick it up
and you know they say hey well you know
maybe we'll try out you know this
one-off project and see if it works with
go and and then they find out it happens
to work really well or are there certain
features of the language that they you
know they say oh we have well we have
project and we know it has you know
these certain design requirements what
languages satisfy this and and then they
find oh you know it's go well that I
mean the typical adoption process for go
is you know as someone at the company
writes some small thing or rewrite some
small thing and go just as like a proof
concept and then you know they build it
and they hand it to their operations
people and the operations people say wow
it's just one static binary okay you
deploy that and then it works and then
it's like wow that was easy
that's the story that I hear a lot and
then it gets you know the next time some
larger project comes along they say hey
maybe we should be using go for this of
course you know they're other people
that have a different approach at splice
who are a music collaboration set up
they said that they you know sort of
evaluated a lot of the languages that
they knew and that are used and sort of
you know when they were building all
their infrastructure they decided to use
code because they said it was not not
specifically because of the features of
the language but because of the focus on
tooling and testing and all the sort of
elements that make writing large
applications more manageable that's very
much a design goal for languages that
were saying earlier so that's that's not
a surprise to what extent this community
participation drive development of the
language we have many many contributors
from your source community we have sort
of a cabal of maybe like a dozen regular
contributors that do a lot of a
substantial amount of work on the core
and you know that varies from time to
time depending on how busy people are
and so on but a lot of the operating
system ports that we've seen have been
done entirely by the community for
instance the windows port of go was done
by a group of volunteers and coordinated
by them and led by them and it's a
really high-quality
port of go and it's part of the core
it's part of the distributions that we
put out and the official distributions
so yeah I mean we are as a project we're
very much a real open source project
it's very much not just Google throwing
blobs of code over the wall we do all
that code review in public
everyone's code is held to the same
level of scrutiny regardless where it
comes from but you know with
said the project is very much led by a
team at Google I mean we're the people
who are paid full time to sit and work
and think about go and so naturally we
have more time and energy to devote to
leading the project and so you know the
the biggest committers the still mostly
Google employees but you know there's
there are some dedicated contributors
from outside Google who are really not
very far behind there are there any
regular conferences there it go user
groups around the world there have been
two small NGO conferences in Tokyo over
the past year and there are you know
these local groups that tend to meet
monthly every couple of months and I've
visited probably more than a dozen of
those around the world in it it's
they're really great I'm really very
happy with the friendliness and
accessibility of the NGO communities
around the world but we're actually
heading towards our first official sort
of large-scale go conference which is go
to Khan and that's happening in Denver
in late April 2014 there's a bunch of
really interesting people speaking and
also myself that should be a lot of fun
I think it's a two-day thing and yeah
I'm really excited for that because
that's the first you know in large-scale
dedicated go conference that's really
been organized also if you're in Europe
we actually have a room at FOSDEM the
big open source conference in Brussels
at the start of February and so if
you're in Europe and coming onto that
please come in check out the GAR room
and we'll be having a sort of small mini
conference inside the conference there I
actually really love that event should
be fantastic but yeah I've also spoken
to other people who were considering
organizing conferences elsewhere and I
think we're really entering the stage
where there'll be a series of dedicated
go conferences in various parts of the
world over the next couple of years and
are there any books that are currently
being written on the language yeah I
mean there are a bunch of great books
and there's a go wiki page that lists
them yeah I mean there's so there's been
plenty of that activity happening even
since day one I think some people
started writing books you know the day
the language was released and so yeah
there's plenty of content out there I
mean when people ask me I'll learn I
still recommend
visiting co-anchor org we have a lot of
articles we have a lot of great
information there
there's just growing all the time but
you know it's definitely worth checking
out some of the other publications that
people have done there are also a lot of
really great go blogs which are also
linked from the wiki contributors write
regular blog posts and they tend to
focus on from in-depth stuff to highly
practical basic level stuff so I think
there's no shortage of learning
materials for getting started with go
all right Andrew well thank you for your
overview of the language really
appreciate it that was thanks for
listening to SC radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to support us you can advertise su
radio by clicking the Digg reddit
delicious or slide buttons on the site
or by talking about us on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on the site
so other listeners can respond to your
comments as well this and all of the
episodes of se radio is licensed under
the creative commons two-point-five
license please see the website for
details thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]